{
  "reference_number": "11430",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Cross party support is essential for the target to be reached and to avoid the risk of the target being changed for political expediency."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes to be more stringent if science or new events dictate, but not less stringent. Guided by the Paris agreement and by any future\n international climate agreements signed by the government."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "No the third budget should only be revised in exceptional circumstances on the recommendation of the Climate Commission and not\n\n on the whim of an incoming government."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Conditional on the recommendation of the Climate Commission and with approval of parliament, but not at the whim of an incoming\n government."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I support Wise Response amended list of considerations which adds 4 new objectives, alters one objective and changes the order of\npriority."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Within 5-6 months."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Implementing a highly precautionary budget that makes highest rates of emissions decline in the first years and does not rely on\noverly complex technology or technical breakthroughs to achieve it. Government to require the Climate Commission includes in their\n\nrecommendations to Parliament clear process and timelines to make it straightforward to turn proposals into firm, funded policies and\nactions. I concur with Wise Response's recommendations."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "As per Wise Response."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "A Fee and Dividend scheme as per the Wise Response."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "To include Wise Response 'desirable' and 'recommended' expertise."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Primarily focussed on mitigation, but recognising that adaptation and mitigation overlap and are both essential aspects of climate\nresilience. Agree with the Wise Response to this question."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I support the preparation of a national climate risk assessment, a national policy plan to address those risks identified, and a\nmonitoring and reporting framework. A risk assessment for New Zealand be undertaken in parallel and that the climate change risk\n\nassessment inform that more general enquiry. A general risk assessment will place climate change risk in a broader context and will\nhelp identify information gaps and opportunities."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I attended a recent talk given at Otago University by a range of experts in their field. The topic was 'Climate Change: Why, when and\nhow do we respond?' I have been interested in finding out more about Climate Change for some time and welcomed this opportunity\n\nto attend the event. It was edifying and somewhat disturbing. I must say the panel were very upbeat about our chances of mitigating\nClimate Change, but the evidence seems very clear that considered action needs to be legislated and acted upon. I'm sure this topic\n\nis not a very popular one with the general populace, however it is something that needs to faced and led by Parliament to ensure the\nfuture for our children and grandchildren. I am glad I was made aware of this submission process by attending the International\nScience Festival in Dunedin. Good Luck - we are in your hands!"
    }
  ]
}
